Finding Aid for John Harris Forster Papers, 1835-1891
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
John Harris Forster Papers 1835-1891
Forster, John Harris, 1822-1894.
0.7 linear ft.
85191 Aa 2
John Harris Forster was a geologist, engineer, surveyor, farmer, and chronicler of life in the Americas in the mid-19th century. As he traveled about North and South America, surveying boundaries, inspecting copper mines, mining gold with the California Forty-Niners, or raising hogs, Forster wrote of his experiences in his journals and used them and his acute memory to describe his travels to family, friends, and an interested public. His journals, correspondence, and speeches are a rich source of social history and geographical and architectural information on life in the areas in which he traveled, including the Great Lakes (Michigan and Wisconsin), Far West, and Central and South America. Forster's papers are of considerable interest for their detailed descriptions of the culture and lifestyle of the native populations he encountered, the terrain and climate of the areas in which he camped and surveyed, and the hardships of life in unsettled or recently settled areas.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Mrs. Elinor Husselman (donor no. 4770 ) and Mrs. Faith Ross (donor no. 5940 ) over a period of time, beginning in 1969.
The collection is open to research.
John Harris Forster was born in 1822 in Erie, Pennsylvania. As a civil and mining engineer and geologist, Forster served as assistant engineer U.S. survey of lakes, river and harbor improvements; assistant engineer Mexican Boundary line (1848-1849); special engineer for construction of Portage Lake and Lake Superior ship canals (late 1850s); and superintendent of the Pewabic and Franklin mines in Houghton county (1860-1865). He was the first state senator elected to represent the Michigan Upper Peninsula (1864-1865), and declined to run for a second term because he found politics too disagreeable. In 1874, Forster and his wife, the former Martha Mullett, retired to his 300 acre Spring Brook farm, located near Williamston, Michigan, where he grew a variety of crops and managed the largest herd of Jersey cattle in the state. He devoted a good deal of his time to the Michigan State Pioneer and Historical Society, of which he was a two-term president. A man of many talents, who was fond of Shakespeare, a friend of education, and highly respected by those who knew him, Forster died in 1894 at Spring Brook.
The John Harris Forster papers are arranged in seven series. Correspondence primarily contains letters written by Forster to various family members, and is arranged chronologically by year. The Thomas Forster series contains materials of John's father, chiefly correspondence and documents pertaining to family and financial matters. Journals and Manuscripts is arranged by year, with titles provided on the contents list. Scrapbook Materials consist of clippings from various newspapers (most of which are unidentified). Forster evidently was a journalist correspondent for these papers, and his columns seem to be excerpts from his journals, with slight modification. His Speeches and Addresses to various Michigan organizations also are based to a large extent on his journals, but there are exceptions, such as the very interesting one detailing life as a Swine-herd in California. Miscellaneous consists mostly of biographical materials and financial documents. Photographs includes portraits and view of the family farm near Williamston, Michigan. For related materials on Forster, including biographical clippings, correspondence to his wife, family documents, and other Forster writings, the researcher should consult the Mullett Family Papers.
Subjects:
Buffalo (N.Y.).; California--Gold discoveries.; Copper mines and mining--Michigan--Upper Peninsula.; Forster, John Harris, 1822-1894.; Gold mines and mining--California.; Green Bay (Wis. and Mich.); Nevada.; Panama.; Surveyors--Michigan.; Silver mines and mining--Nevada.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
California.; Dwellings.; Farms.; Forster, John Harris, 1822-1894.; Panama.; Williamston (Mich.)
Contributors:
Forster, Martha Mullett.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Correspondence (mostly letters written by Forster)
  - Summary of letters written, 1848-1854 (Box 1)
  - 1835-1845 (Box 1)
  - 1856-1859 (transcripts) (Box 1)
  - 1871-1883 (Box 1)
    (includes 1881 letter from Michigan Governor David Jerome)
  - 1837-1863 (Box 1)
    (letters from Forster to his uncle, Major John Harris)
- Thomas Forster (John Harris' father)
  - Correspondence and estate documents (Box 1)
- Journals and Manuscripts
  - 1845 Survey of Green Bay, Wisconsin, and a Voyage from Green Bay to Buffalo (Box 1)
  - 1847 "Rambling Thoughts" (includes transcript) (Box 1)
  - 1849 "Field Notes of a Surveyor in Panama and California", 4 folders
    (re: Mexican-American boundary survey)
    - Manuscript re: preliminary boundary work (Box 1)
    - Original journal, and typed transcript, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Sketchbook (Box 1)
  - 1869 "Report on the Hyko Silver Mining Company's Mines, Pahranagat Mining District, Lincoln County, Nevada" (Box 1)
    (copy of original, which is on deposit at the University of Nevada-Reno)
- Recollections and Reminiscences of Early Life in Lake Superior Country
  - Typed transcripts of articles written in 1869-1870 and published in the Mining Gazette, Houghton, Michigan) (Box 1)
- Scrapbook Materials
  - Clippings of Forster's correspondence to, and columns in, various newspapers), 3 folders (Box 1)
- Speeches and Addresses
  - "Cattle Raising in Spanish America" written in 1885 (Box 1)
  - "Great American Desert of Utah and Nevada)" written in 1886 (Box 1)
  - "Incidents of Travel" written in 1886 (Box 1)
    (pages missing)
  - "My Early Experience as a Farmer and Swine-herd--California, 1854" written in 1891? (Box 1)
  - "A Trip to Tropical America, 1848-1849" written in 1886 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (mostly on farming) (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Biographical materials and financial documents (Box 1)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
  - Framed portraits (2) of John H. Forster and Martha Mullett Forster (Box 1)
    (located in basement storage)